Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to
be looking at specific heat capacity.
So for this particular video, we're going
to go into a short, sweet definition
of what specific heat capacity is.
and how you can use it to calculate heat
and some very common type of problems
that you'll use in introductory general
chemistry to how to use this value.
So whenever specific heat is used, this
is always something that is referred
to as the amount of heat required to
increase something by one degree Celsius.
Now, when we're raising that temperature,
this is for one gram of a substance.
So, specific heat is unique for every
single material that you would come
across in the lab or in your home.
Every single thing takes
so much energy to heat up.
So the way that we like, I like to look at
this is think of it is there are numbers
that are assigned for these, these are,
these are things that have been measured
within laboratory settings and the whole
idea is if I look at both of these two
substances, I have water on the right
hand side, I have iron on the left.
So what exactly will it do?
So if I apply, let's say the
same amount of heat to both.
Well, which one's going to heat faster?
So one way to think about this is if
you put, let's say you put water on the
stove to make, let's say pasta or rice,
or you're just trying to boil it to eat.
And one thing you're going to realize
is like, Oh man, this is taking so long.
I just want this to boil faster.
It usually can take anywhere from five to
maybe 15 minutes, depending on your stove.
It takes a very, very long
time for that to boil.
And that's because it's
absorbing all of that energy.
from the fire in order to
eventually reach boiling.
So now if you can look here,
water has a specific heat of 4.
186 and that's joules
over grams per Celsius.
So the amount of joules, so 4.
186 joules is required to heat
up one gram by one single degree.
Okay.
So that's a lot of energy for each time.
Now you don't usually just
put water directly on a stove.
Sure.
Maybe in a laboratory setting, you might
put in a beaker, but at home, usually
the way that you cook things is using
like, uh, maybe cast iron pans or maybe
aluminum pans, some sort of metal you're
applying directly to that, to the burner.
Now, When you put that on the burner,
does it get hot quickly, right?
So at first it's very cold, but
within probably about five to 10
seconds, you can already start
feeling the heat getting absorbed
within that piece of metal, right?
And now you can really see that
with that lower value here, right?
0.
451.
That's a lot less energy that's
required to heat that up.
So it's going to be a lot less effort.
For the heat to be able to do that.
So that's kind of the idea here of
what we're going to be looking at.
So let's go through the equations.
We'll do some examples and we'll
show, in this video, I'll show
what kind of practice problems that
you will see with specific heat.
And if you like what you see, hit that
like and subscribe button, comment
below, and if there's any other future
videos you'd like to see as well.
And let's go take a look at this type
of problem as we move through this.
So when it comes to calculating
heat, generally in introductory chem,
there's two equations that we'll see.
This video will cover just one,
which is the MCAT equation.
So for all my premeds out there, MCAT
is an exam one day you'll have to take.
So this is one way to easily
remember how to use this.
So you see that MC delta T, think MCAT.
So how can we use this?
Well, let's go over what
each of these letters mean.
So when we see the letter Q,
this is referring to heat.
Which is a form of energy.
Okay, so now that energy value is we're
going to be measuring that in joules So
if you think of jewel like the vape pen,
it's not the same spelling It's jewel as
in j o u l e e as the for the unit, right?
This is the SI unit for energy.
So we have joules now We have M which
you've seen in many different probably
chemistry videos all over the internet.
That is our mass, right?
So we are going to be measuring that in
grams So we have joules is equal to grams.
Now C, this is our specific heat, right?
Where do we get specific heat from?
Well, it's a specific heat capacity.
So that capacity part where that C
comes from, that is what that is for.
So the units for that are
joules over grams by Celsius.
So you can already see that the
grams are going to cancel between
mass and the specific heat.
Okay, so a lot of times when we talk about
specific heat, we'll abbreviate that as
SH, just so that way we're not having
to constantly write what that value is.
Now delta T, this is our
change in temperature.
Okay, so when we talk about delta
T, this is always about the final
temperature minus the initial.
Okay, so this is a little
formula for yourself.
If you see a delta, that's always
final minus initial, and that's going
to be reported in units of Celsius.
So Celsius is going to be used in this
calculation, um, and this is generally
what our units are reported in.
So let's take a look at this.
Now, when we are using this formula,
there's usually two types of problems
that you will generally see, um, when you
are doing these types of calculations.
The first one is usually you're
calculating the amount of heat
that is required either to heat
something or to cool something down.
So heating is generally, it will be
a positive or a positive value when
you are heating it for your Q value.
So you'll, your joules would be
positive or that's endothermic.
If it's a negative value, that's referring
to exothermic or it's releasing heat.
Right, so sign is going to be really
important in these calculations.
So you always want to make sure
you're paying careful attention.
Now the second type of
problem is identifying an
unknown metal, or substance.
Being that specific heat is unique
for every single material, we
can use this to identify things.
So let's try to take a look
at each of these problems.
So that way we can get an
idea of what it is that we're
going to be seeing with them.
All right.
With calculating specific heat
questions, the big thing about these,
they tend to be word problems, meaning
that we need to make sure we are very
organized and how we are writing all
the little pieces that are in a problem.
So let's take a look at this one.
So it says how many
kilojoules of heat are lost?
Okay, so right off the rip,
it's telling you exactly what it
is that we are trying to find.
So we can see how many
kilojoules of heat are lost.
So when that is happening, that tells
you that this is what you are trying to
find, which is our Q value here, right?
So Q, we're going to put a
little question mark next to it.
Let us know this is what
we're trying to find.
Now it says when the body temperature
of a surgery patient with a blood
volume of 5500 milliliters is cooled.
Okay, so now we have
another volume that's here.
We have 5500 milliliters
of blood that is here.
Blood is mainly made up of water.
So we can assume that this is
the same equivalent as water.
Um, we're using a health example
being that there's a lot of health
people that watch this as well.
So we will have to use that
density there to convert to grams
because we will need a mass.
So maybe let's, before we get too
far into this, let's write our mass,
our 5, 500 mLs, We can convert that
using the density that was given and
then we can see mLs cancels mLs and
this is equivalent to 5, 500 grams.
All right, let's take a look at
what else is given in the problem.
So the next thing that is
mentioned is that we had that
this is being cooled from 38.
5 degrees C to 33.
2 degrees C.
So we have these two temperature values.
that are right here in
the middle of the problem.
Now, reading these careful is very,
very important because we need to make
sure we are identifying them properly.
So, we have TI, which is where
you're starting, your initial point.
And this is referred to as 38.
5 degrees C in the problem.
And in the end, it says it goes down,
or we cool the patient down to 33.
2 degrees C.
So what we're going to have to
do is use this to get delta T.
So being that we're going to be using
that MCAT equation from earlier,
so delta T is final minus initial.
So if we take, um, 33.
2, minus it by 38.
5, what we are going to get is 5.
3 degrees C.
when we do the final minus initial.
Okay, now, now that we have all of
our pieces here, what we can now do,
and we also have our specific heat
as well, so I've already highlighted
that earlier, we can plug in all
these pieces into our equation.
So we're trying to find heat, right?
We have our mass, which is 5500 grams.
We are going to multiply that by
the specific heat, which is 4.
186.
Joules per grams by C.
So I'm going to highlight kind of
where all these are coming from.
So this, this first specific
heat is the blue value here.
We have our mass that's
being placed in here.
And then our last, last but not
least, we have our temperature,
which is at negative 5.
3 degrees C.
And we will highlight that as well,
we'll highlight that with purple.
So, and let's move this over so that
you guys can see this equation, because
I'm kind of blocking that a little bit.
Okay, so we have all of our
values here, so what we will do
is take 5500 grams, times it by 4.
186, times it by negative 5.
3, and what we will get in the end is a
negative Q value, which is going to be in
joules, and we will get negative 122 0.
21.
19 or 0.
9 joules for our answer.
Now is this really the
way that you want it?
Well, earlier it mentioned
we want this in kilojoules.
So how do we convert this
number to kilojoules?
Well, if you kind of think of kilo,
right, there are a thousand, there's a
thousand joules for every one kilojoule.
So we can do a little
conversion here for ourselves.
And we can also round it to the correct
number of sig figs in the problem, right?
Because it looks like we had three
sig figs throughout the problem.
So in the very end, it's going
to be negative 122 kilojoules is
going to be our final answer here.
And let's double check that
our sig figs are correct.
Um, we have three sig figs
for all the temperatures.
We have two sig figs for the volume, so we
do need to round this a little bit more.
So this will be 120 joules.
because of significant figures.
There are two sig figs for the volume.
Okay, so we always gotta do our
significant figures in every problem.
If you need help with that type of stuff,
you can refer back to my sig fig videos.
Let's find out the identity
of an unknown metal.
You found a 125 gram old cooking
pot and added 14, 600 joules of
heat to raise the temperature.
From 22 degrees C to 325 degrees C.
What is the identity
of the old cooking pot?
So you want to know what
is it made out of, right?
You want to know is it
something that's worth keeping?
So one thing that we're going to
do here is we're going to list
out all of our important values.
So the first thing that we see is
that we have a mass of 125 grams.
We have a heat value that is hidden
in this problem as well, right?
It's 14, 600, so that is a Q value.
So 14, 600 JUULs, and we
have two temperature values.
So we have a TI of 22 degrees C, and
then we have a t F of 325 degrees C.
So, and just to kind of highlight
where those two values came from, that
was from right here in the problem.
Now that we have all these
different values, the one thing
we got to see is, well, what are
we missing is our C value, right?
So we want to figure out what the
identity is, and generally with these
type of problems, you commonly see them
on exams when it comes to introductory
chem, and we usually get a whole entire
list of different values that you can
use here to try to identify what it is.
Um, a lot of times this might be a
multiple choice question too, so maybe if
you can take your luck at guessing, but
you should know how to do these, right?
You want to get all those points.
So if we have our Q equation,
what we will have to do is
rearrange it to get C by itself.
Now being that m, c, delta,
t are all being multiplied.
What we can do is divide out m and delta
t to cancel them to get c by itself.
So when we do that, we can see mass
cancels mass, and then delta t cancels
delta t, getting us our formula of
q m delta t is equal to c, okay?
So now what we're going to do with
that equation is we're going to plug
in all of the values that we were,
that we were given in the problem.
So we can see that we
have our 14, 600 joules.
We're going to be dividing that, um, times
our, our, dividing it by our mass, right?
So that was 125 grams.
And then we will also be dividing by delta
T, which is our final minus our initial.
So we have our 325 degrees C, and
that's going to be minus 22 degrees C.
Okay, so now, when we plug in all
these values, we have 14, 600.
divided by, and one thing I always
recommend to all students is when
you're using your calculator, use
parentheses to your advantage so
you're not giving the wrong answers
when you are using your calculator.
So it'll be divided by 125
times 325 minus 22 degrees C
when you are plugging that in.
And what you should get in the very
end, so if I kind of show the process,
we should get 14, 600 divided by
37, 875, which will give you a final
number of 385 joules grams by Celsius.
I'm just showing the work because
I know that some of you like
to do the little pieces there.
Right, so that would be our final answer.
Now what we will do is we'll check
it against our chart, and what
we're going to see is that, oh, this
value 385 that we have matches what
we also have for copper up here.
So our final answer in this case
is going to be copper, or the
identity of our unknown metal.
Okay, so copper.
And that is how you can use specific
heat to figure out your identity
of all your missing components.
So these kind of problems, they're
usually really straightforward.
It's more of a plug and play
kind of equations, but you have
to be very organized because
it's more of a physics problem.
So go through it, write down your
variables, and keep practicing.
Thank you so much for watching.
If you like this video, please
hit the like and comment button.
Please hit that subscribe button too, and
I hope to see you here for future videos.
Thank you so much for supporting
the channel, and I look to
see you all in the future.
Bye now!